

Personal Info

- +6281802246688
- williamjcollier4@gmail.com
- Bali, Indonesia

Links

My Webite

Tech freelance website

Linkedin

<u>Instagram</u>

<u>Twitter</u>

Github

Skills

- O Staffing Training
- **O** Teamwork
- HACCP Certification
- Creativity | Innovation
- Culinary Expertise
- O Concept Development
- O Operations Management
- O Menu Development
- O Customer Service
- Resource Procurement
- Adaptability
- Communication
- O Time management
- C Flexibility

William J Collier

Chef | F&B Director | Freelancer

Experienced Executive Chef / F&B Director / Freelance Consultant with 30+ years in diverse establishments like high-end restaurants, yachts, gastro-pubs, cafés, and resorts. Frenchtrained American-born versed in multicultural cuisines and disciplines. Farm-to-table approach blending modern techniques while rooted respectfully in tradition, sustainability and locality. Many of my positions I have had the opportunity as a dual role F&B director as well as my chef responsibilities. The ability to craft amazing dining experiences, menu engineering not only with food but with wine, craft cocktails and spirits. Training and supporting impeccable service standards are something I take great pride in achieving.

Education

Culinary Arts, New York Restaurant School

Culinary Degree, Art Institute of New York City

Work Experience

Executive Chef / GM / Owner, Avenue A, Bali, RI, Berawa, Canggu July 2017 - January 2021

Bali's 1st authentic American Gastro-Pub, known for slow and low BBQ, live rock n roll, craft cocktails, and beer. Established as a top live music venue in Bali. https://www.instagram.com/avenueabali/

- Operations Management: Oversaw day-to-day operations across departments including kitchen, service, bar, HR, and accounting.
- Menu Development: Created and updated food and beverage menus quarterly.
- Social Media Management: Designed and implemented promotions on various social media platforms.
- **Photography**: Captured daily photos of food and bar specials to showcase culinary offerings.
- Inventory Management: Controlled stores and inventory.
- **Cost Control**: Managed food and beverage costs to ensure profitability.

O	Attention to detail
0	Problem Solving
\bigcirc	Decision Making

• **Promotion Creation & Brand Management**: Developed promotions and maintained high-quality brand representation in the market.

F&B Director / Partner, Happy Chappy Restaurant, Bali, RI, Seminyak

July 2014 - June 2017

Pioneering American-Australian dim sum house, featuring modern Chinese fusion cuisine.

- Food & Beverage Operations: Oversee seamless running of restaurant and outlets.
- Cuisine Conceptualization: Instrumental in creating and developing modern fusion Chinese cuisine for diverse palates.
- Systems Development & Training: Implement comprehensive training programs, fostering continuous learning.
- **Team Supervision**: Lead brigade of 4 chefs and team of 60 staff, ensuring quality and expertise.
- Outlet Design & Project Management: Key role in creating and managing Happy Chappy outlets and airport concepts.
- **Inventory & Cost Control**: Ensure efficient operations and maintain profitability.
- Promotions & Brand Management: Drive innovative promotions, maintain brand identity.

Operational Manager, Fumé, Smokehouse & Curing Rooms, Bali, RI, Denpasar, Bali

June 2013 - June 2014

I was integral to a boutique production facility that specialized in the delicate art of curing, hot and cold smoking, and sous vide applications.

- Production Planning & Management: I meticulously planned, managed, and quality-tested a monthly production list of over 50 items, preparing them for both wholesale and retail markets in Bali and Jakarta.
- Food Safety Compliance: Our operations were held to the highest food safety standards, maintaining a high-level H.A.C.C.P certification to ensure the quality and safety of our products.

 Volume Management: An important part of my role was meeting monthly volume goals. We processed between 5-6 metric tons of produce every month, handling all stages from sourcing from farms, to packaging, and finally to distribution.

Executive Chef / Food & Beverage Director, Sentosa Private Villas and Spa, Bali, RI, Seminyak

November 2009 - November 2013

I successfully oversaw the food and beverage operations for this 5-star private resort property with three distinct F&B revenue centers. A key accomplishment during my tenure was the rebranding of the restaurant Blossom into EVO restaurant, lounge, and bar.

- Operations Management:: I innovated our in-villa dining experience by creating Asian and International styled concepts with a focus on ingredient-driven menus, raising the standards of personalized hospitality.
- Systems Development & Training: I implemented comprehensive training programs for all service and kitchen teams, leading to enhanced efficiency and service standards.
- **Culinary Programs**: I developed personalized BBQ programs, creating a unique dining experience for our guests for an exclusive private experience.
- Restaurant Design & Project Management: I was instrumental in the creation, design, and project management of the build-out of the EVO restaurant.
- **Inventory Management**: managed all aspects of stores and inventory to ensure the smooth functioning of our operations.
- **Cost Control**: I oversaw food and beverage costs, ensuring the financial health of our operations.

Executive Chef, Sofitel & Novotel Nusa Dua, Seminyak - Nusa Dua November 2007 - November 2009

Transfered from Novotel Nusa Dua

Responsible for maintaining and overseeing the food & beverage operations for 5 Star Accor Group

Resort Property and repositioning of 4 outlets

• **Operations Management:** Handled day-to-day operations for all 4 kitchens.

- Systems Development & Training: I implemented comprehensive training programs for kitchen teams.
- **Culinary Programs**: I developed personalized experiences and menus for daily-weekly-monthly programs.
- Training: As part of a continuing program to develop all our teams on a daily structured basis with individual tracked mentorship.
- **Inventory Management**: managed all aspects of stores and inventory to ensure the smooth functioning of our operations.
- **Cost Control**: I oversaw food costs, ensuring the financial health of our operations.

Culinary and Management Consultancy, Culinary Consulting INC, Bali

July 2004 - January 2007

Started this culinary consultancy company to provide advice and services to local Bali restaurants. Focusing primarily on menu development & engineering, recipe testing, kitchen design, costing programs, business planning, and even marketing strategies.

Clients:

 Terazo, Batan Waru, Batan Waru Kuta, Fuel Nightclub, Seaside, M.Y Silolona, Canggu Club

Executive Chef, Alila Hotels and Resorts, Ubud & Manggis, Bali, RI, Bali

June 2003 - July 2004

Responsible for maintaining and overseeing the food & beverage operations for two 5 star luxury hotel properties.

Executive Chef / Partner, 231 Ellsworth, San Mateo, CA

January 2000 - February 2003

My 1st restaurant project in Northern California as chef/owner, 4 stars in all publications. Modern approach to California cooking with an emphasis on farm-to-table principles, seasonal, organic.

Chef de Cuisine, The Plumed Horse, California

March 1997 - January 2000

Responsible for the food and beverage as well as banquet operations serving

500-1000 covers per day. Highly regarded in Northern California as being the top

restaurant year after year in the community, a legendary institution. California-

French styled Cuisine with emphasis on organically grown & sustainable products.

Chef de Cuisine / Sous Chef, Kimpton Group, Liberte & Splendido, California

June 1994 - January 1997

Liberté San Francisco's Best new restaurant in 1994, focusing on French inspired

Californian cuisine. Received a promotion within 1 year to take the chef de cuisine

position and the flagship Kimpton restaurant property **Splendido**, California-

Mediterranean inspired.

Executive Sous Chef, La Colombe D'Or, March, The Supper Club, New York City

January 1988 - March 1992

Upon graduating Culinary School I started as an apprentice at La Colombe D'Or, at the time one of New York City's most acclaimed restaurants. I moved through the ranks working all stations under Chef Wayne Nish (The Quilted Giraffe, NYC) eventually moving with him 2 years later to open March and The Supper Club, NYC, as Sous Chef & Executive Sous Chef, respectively.

Tournant, Tavern on the Green, New York City

February 1984 - January 1987

New York Cities Busiest Restaurant serving 1000 to 3500 covers per day. I started

working at Tavern as a Banquet Prep Cook in the evenings while still in 2nd School. I

moved through the brigade quickly, Commis, Saucier, Entremetier, Pastry, and Garde

Manger all within three years.